Before March, 2011, I was a photographic retoucher
قبل مارس 2011، كنت منقحة صور فوتوغرافية
based in New York City.
مستقرة في مدينة نيويورك.
We're pale, gray creatures.
نحن مخلوقات رمادية شاحبة.
We hide in dark, windowless rooms,
نختبئ في الظلام، في غرف بلا نوافذ،
and generally avoid sunlight.
وعادة ما نتفادى ضوء الشمس.
We make skinny models skinnier, perfect skin more perfect,
نجعل العارضات النحيفات أنحف والجلد المثالي أكثر مثالية
and the impossible possible,
والمستحيل ممكنا،
and we get criticized in the press all the time,
ويتم انتقادنا في الصحافة طوال الوقت،
but some of us are actually talented artists
لكن بعضنا في الواقع فنانون موهوبون
with years of experience
بسنوات من الخبرة
and a real appreciation for images and photography.
وتقدير حقيقي للصور والفوتوغرافيا.
On March 11, 2011, I watched from home, as the rest
في ال11 من مارس 2011، قد شاهدت من منزلي، مثل بقية
of the world did, as the tragic events unfolded in Japan.
العالم، أحداث اليابان المأساوية وهي تقع.
Soon after, an organization I volunteer with,
وبعد فترة وجيزة، كانت منظمة أتطوع فيها،
All Hands Volunteers, were on the ground, within days,
"أول هاندس فولنتير" كانوا في الميدان في غضون أيام،
working as part of the response efforts.
يشتغلون كجزء من جهود الاستجابة.
I, along with hundreds of other volunteers,
وأنا مع مئات من المتطوعين الآخرين،
knew we couldn't just sit at home,
عرفت أنه لا يمكننا فقط أن نجلس في بيوتنا،
so I decided to join them for three weeks.
فقررت الانضمام إليهم لثلاثة أسابيع.
On May the 13th, I made my way to the town of Ōfunato.
في ال13 من ماي، توجهت إلى بلدة أوفوناتو.
It's a small fishing town in Iwate Prefecture,
وهي بلدة صيد صغيرة في مقاطعة ايواتي،
about 50,000 people,
حوالي 50,000 شخصا،
one of the first that was hit by the wave.
إحدى أوائل المناطق التي ضربتها الموجة.
The waters here have been recorded at reaching
وقد تم تسجيل مستويات الماء هنا
over 24 meters in height,
بما يتجاوز 24 مترا في العلو،
and traveled over two miles inland.
وقطعت أكثر من ميلين في البر.
As you can imagine, the town had been devastated.
وكما يمكنكم التخيل فإن البلدة قد دمرت.
We pulled debris from canals and ditches.
أخرجنا الحطام من القنوات والخنادق.
We cleaned schools. We de-mudded and gutted homes
ونظفنا المدارس. وأزلنا الوحل والطين عن المنازل
ready for renovation and rehabilitation.
استعداد للتجديد وإعادة التأهيل.
We cleared tons and tons of stinking, rotting fish carcasses
قمنا بتطهير أطنان وأطنان من جثث أسماك متعفنة، نتنة
from the local fish processing plant.
من مصنع معالجة الأسماك المحلي.
We got dirty, and we loved it.
اتسخنا لكننا أحببنا ذلك
For weeks, all the volunteers and locals alike
لأسابيع، جميع المتطوعين والسكان المحليين على حد سواء
had been finding similar things.
كانوا يعثرون على أشياء مماثلة.
They'd been finding photos and photo albums
لقد كانوا يعثرون على صور وألبومات الصور
and cameras and SD cards.
وآلات تصوير وبطاقات SD.
And everyone was doing the same.
والجميع كان يقوم بنفس الشيء.
They were collecting them up, and handing them in to
لقد كانوا يجمعونها ويسلمونها إلى
various places around the different towns for safekeeping.
أماكن مختلفة حول البلدات المختلفة لحفظها في صناديق الآمانات.
Now, it wasn't until this point that I realized
الآن، لم أكن قد أدركت قبل تلك اللحظة
that these photos were such a huge part
أن هذه الصور كانت جزءا كبيرا
of the personal loss these people had felt.
من الخسارة الشخصية التي أحس بها هؤلاء الناس.
As they had run from the wave, and for their lives,
وهم يهربون من الأمواج، للنجاة بحياتهم،
absolutely everything they had,
جميع ما يملكون،
everything had to be left behind.
كان عليهم ترك كل شيء خلفهم.
At the end of my first week there, I found myself
في نهاية أسبوعي الأول هناك، وجدت نفسي
helping out in an evacuation center in the town.
أساعد في مركز للإيواء في مركز البلدة
I was helping clean the onsen, the communal onsen,
كنت أساعد في تنظيف الأونسن الجماعي،
the huge giant bathtubs.
أحواض الاستحمام الكبيرة الضخمة.
This happened to also be a place in the town where
وقد كان ذلك مكانا في البلدة حيث
the evacuation center was collecting the photos.
كان مركز الإجلاء يجمع الصور.
This is where people were handing them in,
كان هذا المكان الذي يسلم فيه الناس الصور،
and I was honored that day that they actually trusted me
وقد تم تكريمي ذلك اليوم بأن وثقوا بي
to help them start hand-cleaning them.
للمساعدة في بدء تنظيفها يدويا.
Now, it was emotional and it was inspiring,
الآن، لقد كان ذلك عاطفيا وملهما،
and I've always heard about thinking outside the box,
وكنت دائما أسمع عن التفكير خارج الصندوق،
but it wasn't until I had actually gotten outside of my box
ولكن لم يكن حتى خرجت حقا من صندوقي
that something happened.
أن حدث شيء.
As I looked through the photos, there were some
وأنا أنظر في الصور، كانت بعضها بعمر
were over a hundred years old,
أكثر من مئة سنة،
some still in the envelope from the processing lab,
بعضها ما زال في المغلف من مختبر المعالجة،
I couldn't help but think as a retoucher
لم أملك إلا أن أفكر أنني كمنقحة
that I could fix that tear and mend that scratch,
أستطيع أن أصلح ذلك التمزق وأرمم ذلك الخدش،
and I knew hundreds of people who could do the same.
وقد كنت أعرف مئات الناس الذين يمكنهم القيام بنفس الشيء.
So that evening, I just reached out on Facebook
وفي ذلك المساء، مددت يدي على الفيسبوك
and asked a few of them, and by morning
وطلبت ذلك من بعضهم، وبحلول الصباح
the response had been so overwhelming and so positive,
كانت الاستجابة إيجابية جداً، وغامرة للغاية،
I knew we had to give it a go.
فعرفت أنه علي أن أجرب الأمر.
So we started retouching photos.
وبالتالي بدأنا بتنقيح الصور.
This was the very first.
كانت هذه أول واحدة.
Not terribly damaged, but where the water had caused
لم تكن متضررة جدا، ولكن حيث سبب الماء
that discoloration on the girl's face
زوال التلون هذا على وجه الفتاة
had to be repaired with such accuracy and delicacy.
كان يجب أن يتم إصلاحه بدقة وحساسية بالغة.
Otherwise, that little girl isn't going to look
وإلا فإن تلك الفتاة الصغيرة لن تبدو
like that little girl anymore, and surely that's as tragic
مثل تلك الفتاة الصغيرة بعد الآن، وذلك كان بالتأكيد بقدر مأساوية
as having the photo damaged.
تلف الصورة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Over time, more photos came in, thankfully,
مع مرور الوقت، وصل المزيد من الصور، لحسن الحظ،
and more retouchers were needed,
وبالتالي احتجنا إلى المزيد من المنقحين،
and so I reached out again on Facebook and LinkedIn,
فمددت يدي مجددا على Facebook وLinkedIn،
and within five days, 80 people wanted to help
وفي غضون خمسة أيام، أراد 80 شخصا المساعدة
from 12 different countries.
من 12 بلدا مختلفاً.
Within two weeks, I had 150 people
خلال أسبوعين، كان لدي 150 شخصا
wanting to join in.
راغبا في الانضمام لي.
Within Japan, by July, we'd branched out
داخل اليابان، من تموز/يوليو، تشعبنا
to the neighboring town of Rikuzentakata,
إلى بلدة ريكوزينتاكا المجاورة،
further north to a town called Yamada.
وكذلك شمالا إلى بلدة يامادا.
Once a week, we would set up our scanning equipment
ومرة واحدة كل أسبوع، نقوم بتثبيت معدات المسح لدينا
in the temporary photo libraries that had been set up,
في مكتبات الصور المؤقتة التي أنشئت،
where people were reclaiming their photos.
حيث كان الناس يستردون صورهم.
The older ladies sometimes hadn't seen a scanner before,
أحيانا لم تكن السيدات الأكبر سنا قد رأين ماسحا ضوئيا من قبل،
but within 10 minutes of them finding their lost photo,
ولكن خلال 10 دقائق من إيجادهم لصورهم المفقودة،
they could give it to us, have it scanned,
يمكنهم إعطاؤها لنا، فيتم مسحها ضوئياً،
uploaded to a cloud server, it would be downloaded
ثم الرفع إلى خادم سحابي، سوف يتم تحميلها
by a gaijin, a stranger,
من طرف غايجين gaijin، غريب،
somewhere on the other side of the globe,
في مكان ما على الجانب الآخر من الكرة الأرضية،
and it'd start being fixed.
وسيتم البدء في إصلاحها.
The time it took, however, to get it back
الوقت الذي استغرقته، على كل حال، لاستردادها
is a completely different story,
هو قصة مختلفة تماما،
and it depended obviously on the damage involved.
ويعتمد بوضوح على الأضرار التي شملتها.
It could take an hour. It could take weeks.
قد تستغرق ساعة. وقد تستغرق أسابيع.
It could take months.
ويمكن أن تستغرق أشهرا.
The kimono in this shot pretty much had to be hand-drawn,
والكيمونو في هذه اللقطة وجب رسمه يدوي إلى حد كبير،
or pieced together, picking out the remaining parts of color
أو تجميعها معا، بانتقاء الأجزاء المتبقية من اللون
and detail that the water hadn't damaged.
والتفاصيل التي لم تكن قد تضررت من المياه.
It was very time-consuming.
لقد كان ذلك يستغرق وقتاً طويلاً جداً.
Now, all these photos had been damaged by water,
الآن، كل هذه الصور قد تضررت بالمياه،
submerged in salt water, covered in bacteria,
غمرت في المياه المالحة، وتغطت بالبكتيريا،
in sewage, sometimes even in oil, all of which over time
في مياه الصرف الصحي، وأحيانا حتى في النفط، كل منها على مر الزمن
is going to continue to damage them,
سوف تستمر في إتلافها،
so hand-cleaning them was a huge part of the project.
وبالتالي فتنظيفها يدويا كان جزء كبيرا من المشروع.
We couldn't retouch the photo unless it was cleaned,
لن نستطيع تنقيحها إلا إن تم تنظيفها،
dry and reclaimed.
جافة ومطالب بها.
Now, we were lucky with our hand-cleaning.
الآن، لقد كنا محظوظين في تنظيفنا اليدوي.
We had an amazing local woman who guided us.
وقد كانت معنا امرأة محلية مدهشة قامت بإرشادنا.
It's very easy to do more damage to those damaged photos.
من السهل جدا إدخال المزيد من الأضرار على تلك الصور التالفة.
As my team leader Wynne once said,
وكما قال لي رئيس الفريق واين في إحدى المرات،
it's like doing a tattoo on someone.
إنها مثل وشم شخص ما.
You don't get a chance to mess it up.
ليست لديك فرصة لتخريبه.
The lady who brought us these photos was lucky,
السيدة التي جلبت لنا هذه الصور كانت محظوظة،
as far as the photos go.
من ناحية الصور.
She had started hand-cleaning them herself and stopped
فقد بدأت بتنظيفها يدويا بنفسها ثم توقفت
when she realized she was doing more damage.
عندما أدركت أنها كانت تقوم بمزيد من الأضرار.
She also had duplicates.
وقد كانت لديها كذلك نسخ.
Areas like her husband and her face, which otherwise
أجزاء مثل زوجها ووجهها، التي لولاها
would have been completely impossible to fix,
لكان من المستحيل تماما لحل المشكلة،
we could just put them together in one good photo,
يمكننا فقط وضعهم معا في صورة جيدة واحدة،
and remake the whole photo.
ونعيد تشكيل الصورة بأكملها.
When she collected the photos from us,
عندما أخذت الصورة من عندنا،
she shared a bit of her story with us.
شاركتنا جزء من قصتها.
Her photos were found by her husband's colleagues
تم العثور على صور لها من طرف زملاء زوجها
at a local fire department in the debris
في قسم إطفاء محلي في الأنقاض
a long way from where the home had once stood,
بعيدا جدا من حيث كان منزلهم،
and they'd recognized him.
وقد تعرفوا عليه.
The day of the tsunami, he'd actually been in charge
في يوم تسونامي، كان في الواقع مسؤولا عن
of making sure the tsunami gates were closed.
التأكد من إغلاق بوابات تسونامي.
He had to go towards the water as the sirens sounded.
كان عليه التوجه نحو المياه لدى سماع صفارات الإنذار.
Her two little boys, not so little anymore, but her two boys
طفلاها الصغيران، لم يعودا صغيرين بعد ذلك، ولكن طفليها
were both at school, separate schools.
كان كلاهما في المدرسة، مدارس مختلفة.
One of them got caught up in the water.
واحد منهم حوصر في الماء.
It took her a week to find them all again
وقد استغرقت أسبوعا للعثور عليهم جميعا مرة أخرى
and find out that they had all survived.
واكتشاف أنهم قد نجوا.
The day I gave her the photos also happened to be
واليوم الذي أعطيتها فيه الصور صدف أنه
her youngest son's 14th birthday.
عيد ميلاد ابنها الأصغر ذي ال14 ربيعا.
For her, despite all of this, those photos
وبالنسبة لها، على الرغم من كل هذا، فإن تلك الصور
were the perfect gift back to him,
كانت الهدية المثالية له،
something he could look at again, something he remembered from before
شيء يمكنه النظر إليه مجددا، شيء تذكره من قبل
that wasn't still scarred from that day in March
شيء لم يشوهه ذلك اليوم في مارس
when absolutely everything else in his life had changed
حين تغير كل شيء في حياته تماما
or been destroyed.
أو تدمر.
After six months in Japan,
بعد ستة أشهر في اليابان،
1,100 volunteers had passed through All Hands,
1,100 متطوع قد مرت عن طريق أول هاندس،
hundreds of whom had helped us hand-clean
مئات منهم ساعدونا في التنظيف اليدوي
over 135,000 photographs,
لأكثر من 135,000 صورة،
the large majority — (Applause) —
الغالبية العظمى-(تصفيق)-
a large majority of which did actually find their home again,
غالبية عظمى منها قد وجدت طريقها لأصحابها مجددا،
importantly.
بشكل أهم.
Over five hundred volunteers around the globe
أكثر من خمسمائة متطوع حول العالم
helped us get 90 families hundreds of photographs back,
ساعدوا في إرجاع المئات من الصور لـ90 أسرة،
fully restored and retouched.
تمت إستعادتها وتنقيحها بالكامل.
During this time, we hadn't really spent more than
خلال هذا الوقت، لم نكن قد قضينا في الواقع أكثر من
about a thousand dollars in equipment and materials,
حوالي آلف دولار في المعدات والمواد،
most of which was printer inks.
وكان معظمها حبر الطابعة.
We take photos constantly.
نلتقط الصور باستمرار.
A photo is a reminder of someone or something,
الصورة هي تذكرة بشخص ما أو بشيء ما،
a place, a relationship, a loved one.
بمكان ما، أو بعلاقة ما، أو بعزيز.
They're our memory-keepers and our histories,
إنها حافظات ذاكرتنا وتاريخنا،
the last thing we would grab
آخر شيء قد تلتقطه
and the first thing you'd go back to look for.
وأول شيء ستعود لتبحث عنه.
That's all this project was about,
وهذا كل ما كان هذا المشروع عليه،
about restoring those little bits of humanity,
حول استعادة تلك القطع الصغيرة من الإنسانية،
giving someone that connection back.
وإعادة ذلك الاتصال إلى أحدهم.
When a photo like this can be returned to someone like this,
إن أمكن إعادة صورة كهذه لشخص كهذا،
it makes a huge difference
فهي تصنع فرقا كبيرا
in the lives of the person receiving it.
في حياة الشخص الذي يحصل عليها.
The project's also made a big difference in the lives of the retouchers.
وقد شكل المشروع كذلك فرقا كبيرا في حياة المنقحين.
For some of them, it's given them a connection
ولبعض منهم، فإنه قد أعطاهم رابطا
to something bigger, giving something back,
بشيء أكبر، إرجاع شيء،
using their talents on something
استخدام موهبتهم في شيء
other than skinny models and perfect skin.
آخر غير العارضات النحيفات والجلد المثالي.
I would like to conclude by reading an email
أود أن أختم بقراءة بريد إلكتروني
I got from one of them, Cindy,
تلقيته من أحدهم، سيندي،
the day I finally got back from Japan after six months.
في اليوم الذي عدت فيها أخيرا من اليابان بعد ستة أشهر.
"As I worked, I couldn't help but think about the individuals
"وأنا أعمل، لم يسعني إلا أن أفكر في الأفراد
and the stories represented in the images.
والحكايات الممثلة في الصور.
One in particular, a photo of women of all ages,
أحدها على وجه الخصوص، صورة لنساء من كل الأعمار،
from grandmother to little girl, gathered around a baby,
من الجدة إلى الطفلة الصغيرة، مجتمعين حول طفل،
struck a chord, because a similar photo from my family,
مست وترا حساسا، لأن صورة مشابهة من عائلتي،
my grandmother and mother, myself,
جدتي وأمي وأنا
and newborn daughter, hangs on our wall.
وابنت حديثة الولادة، معلقة على حائطنا.
Across the globe, throughout the ages,
في جميع أنحاء العالم، على امتداد الأعمار،
our basic needs are just the same, aren't they?"
حاجاتنا الأساسية هي نفسها تماما، أليس كذلك؟"
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم. (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)